An important step in structure-based drug design consists in the prediction of druggable binding sites. Several algorithms for detecting binding cavities, those likely to bind to a small drug compound, have been developed over the years by clever exploitation of geometric, chemical and evolutionary features of the protein.
Predicting ligand binding sites (LBSs) on protein structures, which are obtained either from experimental or computational methods, is a useful first step in functional annotation or structure-based drug design for the protein structures. In this work, the structure-based machine learning algorithm ISMBLab-LIG was developed to predict LBSs on protein surfaces with input attributes derived from the three-dimensional probability density maps of interacting atoms, which were reconstructed on the query protein surfaces and were relatively insensitive to local conformational variations of the tentative ligand binding sites. The prediction accuracy of the ISMBLab-LIG predictors is comparable to that of the best LBS predictors benchmarked on several well-established testing datasets. More importantly, the ISMBLab-LIG algorithm has substantial tolerance to the prediction uncertainties of computationally derived protein structure models. As such, the method is particularly useful for predicting LBSs not only on experimental protein structures without known LBS templates in the database but also on computationally predicted model protein structures with structural uncertainties in the tentative ligand binding sites.
Transcription factors are crucial for sequence‐specific control of transcriptional
regulation. Classically, the computational prediction of transcription factor binding
sites (TFBS) depends on position weight matrices (PWMs) (Wingender et al., 2001),
which give weights to each nucleotide at each position. These models strongly suggest
that each nucleotide participates independently in the corresponding DNA–protein
interaction and does not account for flexible length motifs.
In recent years, a large number of methods have been developed for the prediction of protein
function and protein–ligand binding sites.
These methods can be broadly
divided into sequence-based methods and structure-based methods.
Sequence-based methods that predict protein–ligand binding sites and their interacting
ligand-binding site residues are those that use information from evolutionary conservation and/or
sequence similarity of homologous proteins. These methods can be broadly categorised into methods
that utilize machine learning (Multi-RELIEF [11], TargetS [12], LigandRF [13], and OMSL [14]),
methods that utilize only position-specific scoring matrices or PSSMs (INTREPID [15], DISCERN [16],
ConSurf [17], and ConFunc [18]) and graph-based methods such as Conditional Random Field
(CRF) [19]. The advent of including machine learning-based strategies into sequence-based methods
has resulted in improved method sensitivity. Machine learning is applied to PSSMs or multiple
sequence alignment-based properties using various alternative strategies, examples of which will
now be discussed.
Many of the sequence-based methods, such as Multi-RELIEF [11], deploy machine learning
methods to directly interpret multiple sequence alignment profiles. Multi-RELIEF works by
estimating the functional specificity of residues from a multiple sequence alignment using local
conservation properties. This method uses a machine learning technique called RELIEF [20] for
feature selection and weighting, using a binary classification to discriminate features from two classes.
A residue’s local specificity is determined by comparing the sequence with the closest homologue
in each of the two classes (same class and opposite class), using global sequence identity to find
the nearest neighbour sequence. If a residue has high local specificity to one pair of classes, it is
labelled as relevant. Furthermore, global sequence similarity is considered while scoring each residue
locally [11]. This results in the prediction of residues comprising a putative ligand binding site.
In contrast, LigandRFs [13] uses a random forest-based algorithm to predict protein–ligand
binding site residues. LigandRFs extracts 544 amino acid properties from the AAindex database [21],
which are then compared using the Matthews correlation coefficient. Each of the 544 properties are
ranked in relation to the number of their related properties. The properties are filtered to remove all
properties related to the top property; this removes redundant properties, which do not add any new
information. This process is continued through the list until 34 properties remain. These properties
relate to specific features crucial for determining putative binding site residues. The properties are
then applied over a seven residue sliding window of a PSI-BLAST [22] profile. A 1  238 vector
is used to represent the 34 amino acid properties for each seven residue window. A random forest
is then utilized to learn the relationship between the large vector and the binding or non-binding
residue properties
Structure-based methods are those that exploit information from 3D atomic coordinates
(either predicted from sequence or derived from experiments). These methods either predict
the location of the ligand binding site and/or the putative ligand binding site residues. Such
methods can be further sub-categorised into: 1. Geometric-based methods (FINDSITE [25],
LigDig [26], LISE [27], PatchSurfer2.0 [28], Surflex-PSIM [29], EvolutionaryTrace [30], PRANK [31],
a Two-dimensional replica-exchange method [32], FMO-RESP [33], MapReduce approach [34],
TIFP [35], ProGolem [36], a Chemogenomics approach [37], ProPose [38], FunFHMMer [39],
mFASD [40], ProBis [41,42], and CavBase [43,44]); 2. Energetic methods (SITEHOUND [45],
VISCANA [46], SiteComp [47], and FTMap [48]); 3. Miscellaneous methods, which use information
from homology or template-based modelling (FunFOLD3 [3,4], COACH [49], COFACTOR [50],
GalaxySite [51], GASS [52], VISM-CFA [53], and PLIP [54]), Surface accessibility based methods
such as LigSiteCSC [55], in addition to Physicochemical properties exploited by Andersson and
colleagues [56]. Examples of different methods from each sub-category are now described, in addition
to their limitations.
Structure-based methods for prediction of protein–ligand binding sites have a number of
limitations, including the following: 1. If a 3D model or experimental structure cannot be obtained,
then it is not possible to make a prediction; in such cases the solution is to rely on purely
sequence-based methods. 2. If templates with the same fold as the target protein that contain
biologically relevant ligands cannot be detected, then it is not possible to make a prediction. 3. Most
prediction servers, such as COACH [49] and FunFOLD [3,4,57], utilize in-house structure prediction
pipelines to construct models for protein–ligand interaction predictions that may not always produce
the best quality model for every target, which may result in over- and under-predicted protein–ligand
binding sites. Nevertheless, despite these shortcomings, prediction methods are constantly under
development and improvements can be gauged via the rigorous independent blind assessment
binding , site , interaction , ligand , drug , design
