Protein structure prediction is the method of inference of protein’s 3D structure from its amino acid sequence through the use of computational algorithms.
Protein structure prediction is the inference of the three-dimensional structure of a protein from its amino acid sequence—that is, the prediction of its folding and its secondary and tertiary structure from its primary structure. Structure prediction is fundamentally different from the inverse problem of protein design. Protein structure prediction is one of the most important goals pursued by bioinformatics and theoretical chemistry; it is highly important in medicine (for example, in drug design) and biotechnology (for example, in the design of novel enzymes). Every two years, the performance of current methods is assessed in the CASP experiment (Critical Assessment of Techniques for Protein Structure Prediction). A continuous evaluation of protein structure prediction web servers is performed by the community project CAMEO3D.
The protein structure can be considered as a sequence of secondary structure elements, such as α helices and β sheets, which together constitute the overall three-dimensional configuration of the protein chain. In these secondary structures regular patterns of H bonds are formed between neighboring amino acids, and the amino acids have similar Φ and Ψ angles.
Proteins may be classified according to both structural and sequence similarity. For structural classification, the sizes and spatial arrangements of secondary structures described in the above paragraph are compared in known three-dimensional structures. Classification based on sequence similarity was historically the first to be used. Initially, similarity based on alignments of whole sequences was performed. Later, proteins were classified on the basis of the occurrence of conserved amino acid patterns. Databases that classify proteins by one or more of these schemes are available. In considering protein classification schemes, it is important to keep several observations in mind. First, two entirely different protein sequences from different evolutionary origins may fold into a similar structure. Conversely, the sequence of an ancient gene for a given structure may have diverged considerably in different species while at the same time maintaining the same basic structural features. Recognizing any remaining sequence similarity in such cases may be a very difficult task. Second, two proteins that share a significant degree of sequence similarity either with each other or with a third sequence also share an evolutionary origin and should share some structural features also. However, gene duplication and genetic rearrangements during evolution may give rise to new gene copies, which can then evolve into proteins with new function and structure.
Secondary structure prediction is a set of techniques in bioinformatics that aim to predict the local secondary structures of proteins based only on knowledge of their amino acid sequence. For proteins, a prediction consists of assigning regions of the amino acid sequence as likely alpha helices, beta strands (often noted as "extended" conformations), or turns. The success of a prediction is determined by comparing it to the results of the DSSP algorithm (or similar e.g. STRIDE) applied to the crystal structure of the protein. Specialized algorithms have been developed for the detection of specific well-defined patterns such as transmembrane helices and coiled coils in proteins.[1]

The best modern methods of secondary structure prediction in proteins reach about 80% accuracy;[3] this high accuracy allows the use of the predictions as feature improving fold recognition and ab initio protein structure prediction, classification of structural motifs, and refinement of sequence alignments. The accuracy of current protein secondary structure prediction methods is assessed in weekly benchmarks such as LiveBench and EVA.
Protein structure prediction methods attempt to determine the native, in vivo structure of a given amino acid sequence. To do so, knowledge of protein structure determinants are critical: the hydrophobicity and hydrophilicity of residues, electrostatic interactions, hydrogen and covalent bonds, van der Waals interactions, bond angle stresses, and enthalpy and entropy.

There are two important facts about the determinants mentioned: First, information about them, and thus a protein's structure, is contained entirely within the sequence (in addition to knowledge of the solvent). Second, they are all measurements of physical properties (energies, actually). Assuming a protein can take its native conformation in solvent, without the aid of protein chaperones, we have enough information to predict protein structures ab initio (from basic principles). However, many of the determinants are not known precisely enough, or may be too compute-intensive (computationally non-tractable).

In the absence of feasible ab initio methods, protein structure prediction has turned to knowledge-based methods: homology modeling and protein fold recognition methods being the two major and complementary approaches taken.

The low amount of accuracy (usually ranging 50-70%) is a disadvantage for both methods. Another disadvantage for both is that known structures have to be available. The methods would fail when predicting the structure of a novel protein. Additionally, they tend to fail in predicting structures which are particularly sensitive to sequence differences, such as with random coils.
Homology modeling
For homology modeling, the amino acid sequence of a protein with unknown structure is aligned against sequences of proteins with known structures. High degrees of homology (very similar sequences across and between the proteins) can be used to determine the global structure of the protein with unknown structure and place it into a certain fold category. Lower degrees of homology may still be used to determine local structures, an example being the Chou-Fasman method for predicting secondary structure. An advantage for homology modeling methods is the lack of dependence on the knowledge of physical determinants.
Fold recognition
Fold recognition methods take a complementary approach. With these, structures, not sequences, are aligned. With the method called "threading," the sequence of a protein with unknown structure is forced to take the conformation of the backbone (protein sans side chains) of a protein with known structure. The better the physical determinants measure for each attempt, the better the score for the alignment. These methods tend to be more compute-intensive than homology modeling methods, but they give more confidence in the physical viability of the results.
rediction of protein structures can be classified into two major categories viz. (i) Prediction of secondary structure and (ii) Prediction of tertiary (3-D) structure. Prediction of secondary structure of proteins attempts to locate segments of the polypeptide chain adopting the α-helical or β-strand structure. Regions that are devoid of these regular secondary structural elements are considered to adopt coil conformation. In tertiary structure prediction, one attempts to predict the three-dimensional structure of a protein or the native structure. While so far this has remained an elusive goal, different methods have been developed to press forward to the attainment of this goal. 
Protein structure prediction from amino acid sequence has been one of the most challenging aspects in computational structural biology despite significant progress in recent years showed by critical assessment of protein structure prediction (CASP) experiments. When experimentally determined structures are unavailable, the predictive structures may serve as starting points to study a protein. If the target protein consists of homologous region, high-resolution (typically <1.5 Å) model can be built via comparative modelling. However, when confronted with low sequence similarity of the target protein (also known as twilight-zone protein, sequence identity with available templates is less than 30 %), the protein structure prediction has to be initiated from scratch. Traditionally, twilight-zone proteins can be predicted via threading or ab initio method. Based on the current trend, combination of different methods brings an improved success in the prediction of twilight-zone proteins. In this mini review, the methods, progresses and challenges for the prediction of twilight-zone proteins were discussed.
structure , prediction , modeling , twilight , helices , conformation , sheets
