sequence assembly refers to aligning and merging fragments from a longer DNA sequence in order to reconstruct the original sequence. This is needed as DNA sequencing technology cannot read whole genomes in one go, but rather reads small pieces of between 20 and 30000 bases, depending on the technology used. Typically the short fragments, called reads, result from shotgun sequencing genomic DNA,
The problem of sequence assembly can be compared to taking many copies of a book, passing each of them through a shredder with a different cutter, and piecing the text of the book back together just by looking at the shredded pieces. Besides the obvious difficulty of this task, there are some extra practical issues: the original may have many repeated paragraphs, and some shreds may be modified during shredding to have typos. Excerpts from another book may also be added in, and some shreds may be completely unrecognizable.
DNA sequencing refers to sequencing methods for determining
the order of the nucleotide bases - adenine, guanine, cytosine, and thymine - in a molecule of DNA.
From the later 1970's to 2005, Sanger sequencing was the dominating technology for sequencing.
Despite the development of automated techniques, currently the longest reads (also called fragments
or sequencing reads) available are obtained using Sanger's method, consisting 500 􀀀 1000 consecutive
base pairs of DNA in any one read.
To sequence a long molecule of DNA, or even a whole genome, generally shotgun sequencing is used.
History:
Originally, shotgun sequencing was applied to small viral genomes (1977) and to 30 􀀀 40kb segments
of larger genomes.

The shotgun sequencing method using the Sanger sequencing operates as follows:
The target DNA molecule is broken into small fragments, each of which is sequenced. The target
sequence is assembled by searching for overlaps between the sequences of individual fragments.
Sequence assembly refers to aligning and merging many fragments of a much longer target DNA
sequence in order to reconstruct the target sequence.

Assume we want to determine the sequence A = a1a2 : : : aL of a given DNA molecule.
Shotgun sequencing of the molecule produces a set of reads
Fragment Assembly problem: The Fragment Assembly problem is to reconstruct the sequence A
of a DNA molecule from a set of fragments
As described, initial DNA sequencing reactions generate short sequence reads from
DNA clones. The average length of the reads is about 500 bases. To assemble a whole
assembly , sequencing ,  fragments , shotgun , reconstruct , contigs
genome sequence, these short fragments are joined to form larger fragments after
removing overlaps. These longer, merged sequences are termed contigs, which are
usually 5,000 to 10,000 bases long. A number of overlapping contigs can be further
merged to form scaffolds (30,000–50,000 bases, also called supercontigs), which are
unidirectionally oriented along a physical map of a chromosome
Overlapping
scaffolds are then connected to create the final highest resolution map of the
genome.
Correct identification of overlaps and assembly of the sequence reads into contigs
are like joining jigsaw puzzles, which can be very computationally intensive when
dealing with data at the whole-genome level. The major challenges in genome assembly
are sequence errors, contamination by bacterial vectors, and repetitive sequence
regions. Sequence errors can often be correctedby drawing a consensus fromanalignment
of multiple overlapped sequences. Bacterial vector sequences can be removed
using filtering programs prior to assembly.
assembly , sequencing ,  fragments , shotgun , reconstruct , contigs