Phylogeny is the evolution of a genetically related group of organisms via the study of protein or gene evolution by involving the comparison of homologous sequences.
Phylogenetic tree reconstruction is a powerful and visually intuitive approach for inferring evolutionary relationships between microbial sequences
A phylogenetic tree or evolutionary tree is a branching diagram or "tree" showing the evolutionary relationships among various biological species or other entities—their phylogeny (/faɪˈlɒdʒəni/)—based upon similarities and differences in their physical or genetic characteristics. All life on Earth is part of a single phylogenetic tree, indicating common ancestry.
One central field in biology is to infer the relation between species. Do they possess a common
ancestor? When did they separate from each other? The relation is presented in form of a tree
with a unique root. Leaves of the tree are currently observable species and are called taxa. The
branches represent the relationship (“is ancestor of”) between nodes. The root is the start of life
on earth. From the first living organism all other life forms are derived. An edge in the tree of life
means that a species is the ancestor of another one. A node means a split of a species into two.
The construction of the tree of life is called phylogeny (phylo = tribe and genesis). Classical
biological phylogeny is divided into the cladistic and the phenetic approach. Cladistic trees are
based on conserved characters and phenetic trees on the measure of distance between the leaves
of the tree (the phenetic approach considers the distance as a whole and not based on single features).
Problems of the phenetic approach are simultaneous development of features and different
evolution rates. There may be convergent evolution e.g. finding the best form in water.
With molecular phylogenetics, the differences
between organisms are measured on the proteins and RNA coded in the DNA, i.e. on amino acid
and nucleotide sequences. In Fig. 5.4 the species tree and the gene tree for -hemoglobin are
depicted – they match. Molecular phylogenetics is more precise than its counterpart based on external
features and behavior and can also distinguish small organism like bacteria or even viruses.
Further advantages of molecular phylogenetics are that the DNA must be inherited and connects
all species, the molecular phylogenetics can be based on mathematical and statistical methods
and is even model-based as mutations can be modeled, remote homologies can be detected, the
distance is not only based on one feature, but on many genes.
There are difficulties in constructing a phylogenetic tree. First, different regions in the DNA
mutate at different rates. Which means that the distances may look differently. Secondly, horizontal
transfer of genetic material (Horizontal Gene Transfer, HGT) between species is possible,
Genetic data is often used to infer evolutionary relationships among a collection of viruses, bacteria, animal or plant species, or other operational taxonomic units (OTU). A phylogenetic tree depicts such relationships and provides a visual representation of the estimated branching order of the OTUs. Tree estimation is unique for several reasons, including the types of data used to represent each OTU; the use of probabilistic nucleotide substitution models; the inference goals involving both tree topology and branch length, and the huge number of possible trees for a given sample of a very modest number of OTUs, which implies that finding the best tree(s) to describe the genetic data for each OTU is computationally demanding.
he result of the tree construction is a decision about the most likely evolutionary relationships. Fundamentally, tree-construction programs decide which sequences had common ancestors.


Distance based phylogeny programs start by using sequence comparisons to estimate evolutionary distances:

they apply a model of evolution such as a mutation data matrix, to calculate a score for each pair of sequences,
this score is stored in a "distance matrix" ...
... and used to estimate a tree that groups sequences with close relationships together. (e.g. by using an NJ, Neigbor Joining, algorithm).
They are fast, can work on large numbers of sequences, but are less accurate if genes evolve at different rates.

Parsimony based phylogeny programs build a tree that minimizes the number of mutation events that are required to get from a common ancestral sequence to all observed sequences. They take all columns into account, not just a single number per sequence pair, as the Distance Methods do. For closely related sequences they work very well, but they construct inaccurate trees when they can't make good estimates for the required number of sequence changes.


ML, or Maximum Likelihood methods attempt to find the tree for which the observed sequences would be the most likely under a particular evolutionary model. They are based on a rigorous statistical framework and yield the most robust results. But they are also quite compute intensive and a tree of the size that we are building in this assignment is a challenge for the resources of common workstation (runs about an hour on my computer). If the problem is too large, one may split a large problem into smaller, obvious subtrees (e.g. analysing orthologues as a group, only including a few paralogues for comparison) and then merge the smaller trees; this way even very large problems can become tractable.

ML methods suffer less from "long-branch attraction" - the phenomenon that weakly similar sequences can be grouped inappropriately close together in a tree due to spuriously shared differences.

tree ,  evolution , phylogeny , phylogenetic , ancestor , branch
Bayesian methods don't estimate the tree that gives the highest likelihood for the observed data, but find the most probably tree, given that the data have been observed. If this sounds conceptually similar to you, then you are not wrong. However, the approaches employ very different algorithms. And Bayesian methods need a "prior" on trees before observation.